Division of Invertebrate Paleontology Archives
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
- Field Notebooks, Series IV
  - Undated., 001292
    - Field notes. field notes/collecting information from Samuel J. Ciurca, Jr.; mostly Silurian of New York, Eurypterida, 000821
    - Field notes. Field Notebooks, Joseph St. Jean, 000871
    - Field notes. Strat. columns, field notebook, property survey map, 000907
    - Field notes. locality information Martin Quarry, Jo's Quarry, Burke Creek/Wood Creek, 000921
    - Field notes. Cambrian Marjum Fm, House Range, Utah (Gogia), 000930
    - Field notes. Field notes: Moroccan localities - Peter Van Roy and Sarah Tweedt, 000960
    - Notebook. Notebook, 000909
    - Notebook. Field notes, stratigraphic sections, and locality information for stromatoporoid collecting in upstate NY, 000911
- Specimen Information, Series V
  - Faunal Lists., 001294
    - Faunal charts. Faunal charts & stratigraphic sections: Arisaig, Nova Scotia., 1969; 000003
    - Faunal list. Faunal and Locality list and catalog: Iberger Kalk, Devonian; Germany., 1889; 000380
    - Faunal list. Faunal lists: Germany., 1904; 000377
    - Faunal list. Faunal lists: Czechoslovakia, Bohemia; Barrande Stages, 1912; 000378
    - Faunal list. List of species with age and locality (Kruizinga), and locality map (Wanner): Timor. 1921, 1934, 1953, 000361
    - Faunal list. Faunal and Locality list: Germany., 1924; 000379
    - Faunal list. Faunal list of id'd graptolites, New Brunswick, Canada., 1929; 000528
    - Faunal list. Faunal information: Utah., 1958; 000526
    - Faunal list. Faunal information; Late Triassic & Early Jurassic of Nova Scotia. exerpts from Atlantic Geology; abstract by Cameron & Jones. 1986 ?, 000689
    - Faunal list. Faunal information; Early Jurassic of Nova Scotia. exerpts from Programs & Summaries 10th annual open house & review of activities, Nov. 19 & 20, 1986, Cameron article. [Volume=N.12], 000690
    - Faunal list. Faunal information; Early Jurassic of Connecticut. exerpts from Rocks & Minerals; article by McDonald, [Volume=v.70,n.6], 1995; 000692
  - Ledgers. Catalogs of specimen numbers., 001295
    - Catalog of identifications. Catalog of brachiopod collection and other fossils and localities: Europe, North America., 1882; 000219
    - Catalog [ledger] of Silurian fossils, numbers 1-2310, 1867; 002700
    - Catalog [ledger] of Devonian fossils, numbers 1-312, 1867; 002701
    - ledger. Catalog (ledger) of Invertebrate Paleontology specimen numbers. [Volume=v.1; YPM nos. 000001 - 004999], 1993; 000407
    - ledger. Catalog (ledger) of Invertebrate Paleontology specimen numbers. [Volume=v.2; YPM nos. 005000 - 010000], 1993; 000408
    - ledger. Catalog (ledger) of Invertebrate Paleontology specimen numbers. [Volume=v.3; YPM nos. 010001 - 015000], 1993; 000409
    - ledger. Catalog (ledger) of Invertebrate Paleontology specimen numbers. [Volume=v.4; YPM nos. 015001 - 019925], 1993; 000410
    - ledger. Catalog (ledger) of Invertebrate Paleontology specimen numbers. [Volume=v.5; YPM nos. 019926 - 025150], 1993; 000411
    - ledger. Catalog (ledger) of Invertebrate Paleontology specimen numbers. [Volume=v.6; YPM nos. 025151 - 030000], 1993; 000412
    - ledger. Catalog (ledger) of Schuchert Brachiopod specimen numbers. [Volume=v.7; Schuchert Brachiopod nos. S0001 - S3705], 1993; 000413
    - ledger. Catalog (ledger) of Braun-Schuchert specimen numbers. [Volume=v.8; Braun Schuchert specimen nos. BS0001 - BS0775], 1993; 000414
    - ledger. Peabody Museum, Catalog (ledger) of Cretaceous Fossils, 1868. Marsh. [Volume=v.1; Old Vert. Paleo. specimen nos. 1 - 468 (partial series)], 1993; 000415
    - ledger. Peabody Museum, Catalog of Cretaceous Fossils, 1868. [Volume=v.2; Old Vert. Paleo. specimen nos. 5000 - 5275], 1993; 000416
    - ledger. Peabody Museum, Catalog (ledger) of Tertiary Fossils, 1867. [Volume=v.2; Old Vert. Paleo. specimen nos. 1 - 823], 1993; 000417
  - Specimen Lists., 001293
    - Catalog of identifications. Dartmouth College Museum, Catalog [ledger] of Paleontology, Parts 1 & 2 (Montshire Museum of Science), 000825
    - Catalog of identifications. General Inventory, Galloway - St. Jean Collection of Stromatoporoids, 000872
    - Catalog of identifications. Catalog and notes, Galloway - St. Jean Stromatoporoid Collection, 000873
    - Specimen List. 1861 Catalog of Invertebrate Fossils: Europe.; 2 lists of fossils from Europe sent to Peabody, 000174
    - Specimen List. S.S. Strong collection of Pennsylvanian, Francis Creek Sh Mbr of Carbondale Fm invertebrates from Mazon Creek, Grundy County, Illinois, 1869; 000824
    - Specimen List. Catalog of Devonian Heldeberg fossils: New York., 1899; 000153
    - Specimen List. Catalog of fossil insects collected from Haverkampf Farm 3 mi SE of Lawrence, Kansas: Kansas., 1903; 000268
    - Specimen List. Catalog of Brachiopoda shipped to C. Schuchert by F. Krantz. 27, 1903; 000916
    - Specimen List. Catalog of Mesozoic Porifera: Europe., 1905; 000201
    - Specimen List. Catalog of crinoids & blastoids: Iowa., 1905; 000203
    - Specimen List. Catalog of Hunton Fm collections: Oklahoma. 1905, 1906, 1907, 000235
    - Specimen List. List of taxa in collection: Europe., 1905; 000354
    - Specimen List. Specimen and locality catalog for Ordovician graptolites: Victoria, Australia., 1934; 000334
    - Specimen List. list of fusulinid thin sections: Russia., 1936; 000388
    - Specimen List. Catalog of foraminifera: Colorado, South Dakota, Wyoming., 1958; 000162
    - Specimen List. Catalog of foraminifera: New Jersey., 1961; 000211
    - Specimen List. Catalogue of type invertebrate fossils of the Geological Survey of Canada, 1977; 000892
    - Specimen List. Identifications of insects from Newark Supergroup, Solite Quarries, Virginia, North Carolina, 1989; 000657
    - Specimen List. List of specimens donated to YPM., 1995; 000522
    - Specimen List. List of & descriptions of Hitchcock's non-type trace fossils (ichnofossil) from Triassic of Massachusetts; Film roll & negative numbers: list of other trace fossils with YPM #s from 160604-160758 and 35841, 10184, 31303, 32647, 6914, 7413, 38253, 33164 - all with no loc nos. as of Dec. 2004. 1999, 2000 (locs done as of 2009); 160759 and beyond are in room 5 and not entered, 000748
    - Specimen List. Notes on brachiospongid fossils: Kentucky., 000241
    - Specimen List. Catalog of ammonite collection: England, Germany., 000345
    - Specimen List. List of specimens: mixed Paleozoic and Mesozoic., 000385
    - Specimen List. Ostracoda listed in well logs of various oil companies; Texas; Louisiana; Eocene, 000822
    - Models of Foraminifera plates and associated lists, 000981
  - Specimen Sketches & Images., 002473
    - Sketch done by Fred Hotchkiss 21 Apr 2002 of Calyptactis specimen (YPM 526759), 002472
    - Notes pertaining to YPM IP 534359 and a sketch of a similar specimen (ROM 56190a), 2016; 002716
    - Notes and sketches pertaining to YPM IP 237234, 543045-543049., 2018; 003219
    - Notes and sketches pertaining to Hunsruck specimens from YPM.12758 (YPM IP 543086, 543088, 2018; 003220
    - Several x-rays of IP.539731., 003090
  - Specimen information., 002734
    - Locality information including annotated maps; additional specimen documentation including observations by Fred Hotchkiss., 2003; 002743
    - Notes concerning asterozoan fossils received from Fred Hotchkiss as part of accn. YPM.12519, 2007-2017; 002735
    - Correspondence concerning latex peels of ophiuroids from Swatara Gap., 2007-2017; 002736
    - Observations and photographs of ophiuroid specimens collected on a peninsula in Cedar Creek Reservoir, Franklin County, Alabama (IPF.03004)., 003023
- Miscellaneous, Series VI
  - Accession card catalog. Peabody Museum card catalog of accession numbers from IP Div file cabinets. Note on file drawer "Circle Series: 1862-1869, Red numbers indicate card sequence in Invertebrate Paleontology accession catalog., 002704
  - Biographical Material., 001296
    - Biographical Material. List of portraits & paintings in Peabody Museum., 1985; 000723
    - Biographical Material. Non-peer reviewed publications of and about Samuel J. Ciurca (newsletters, newspaper articles, etc.); mostly Silurian of New York, Eurypterida, 1997-2018; 000841
    - Biographical Material. Handwriting samples of the following individuals:, 000703
    - Biographical Material. Obituary of Carl Wiman, 000808
    - Biographical Material. Obituaries and memorials: Charles Schuchert, 000928
    - Biographical Material. Miscellaneous documentation and memorabilia from the family of Charles Schuchert, 000929
    - Newspaper article. Newspaper clippings on Helen Ross & scaphitid ammonoid (Discoscaphites rossi) named after her. And Museum brochure. Timber Lake Topics, 1993; 000686
  - Correspondence., 001297
    - Correspondence. Correspondence regarding localities, specimens, field trips, donations, 1974-1994; 003144
    - Miscellaneous. Postcard of echinoderm display in Invertebrate Hall, Peabody Museum of Natural History, Yale University. Postcard includes Crawfordsville crinoid that was stolen, ca. 1990., 000587
    - Miscellaneous. Letters of understanding regarding the transfer of ownership of the Joseph St. Jean collection of Stromotoporoidea from him (at University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill) to Yale University; and other related documents., 2001; 000753
    - Papers, notes, correspondence. Notes by Sanderson, and list of specimens by W.A. Kelly (see correspondence): Northwest Territories, Alberta., 1925; 000351
    - Papers, notes, correspondence. letter from Newberry re ichnofossils (Rusophycus), YPM 300859, 300860, 300861, 300862, 300863, 300864, 300865, 000883
    - Letter dated 10 June 1964 from Dr. R. Prokop (Ustredni ustav geologicky, Praha) to Dr. H. B. Fell (Harvard MCZ) accompanying two casts of a specimen of Archegonaster pentagonus. Also, the lid of the original shipping box., 002724
  - Data Capture Sheets., 001302
    - Data capture sheet. Data capture sheets for W.A. Parks (1910); ip.r.0486., 000426
    - Data capture sheet. Data capture sheets for R. Ruedemann (1933; ip.r.00593., 000427
    - Data capture sheet. Data capture sheets for V.J. Okulitch (1943); IP.R.00475., 000425
    - Data capture sheet. Data capture sheets for R. Ruedemann (1947); ip.r.00597., 000428
    - Data capture sheet. Data capture sheets for A.K. Miller & W.L. Younguist (1947); ip.r.00458., 000431
  - Guest Books. Guest Books / Visitor Logs., 002432
    - Invertebrate Paleontology, Peabody Museum visitor (guest) book: 1987-2002., 000772
  - Loan Correspondence. Assorted correspondence associated with a number of loans and researchers. From the divisional filing cabinet "Loan et al, Correspondence." Fourteen document boxes worth of material., 002687
    - Old loan forms from the Smithsonian for rugose specimens. USNM invoices 193 and 203. Also a note about getting type material from Bassler., 1911-1916; 002698
    - Old loan form for specimens sent on loan to Ray Bassler at the USNM. According to May Dasch, a duplicate copy of this invoice was found in Dunbar's file of "old loans - returned" with an annotation that Bassler still retained two specimens. Both forms are in this archive. The two specimens potentially still at the USNM do not provide enough information at present to track whether they have actually been returned to the Peabody Museum., 1931; 002692
    - Old loan forms for specimens sent on loan to Ben F. Howell at Princeton. One was for 6 pieces of rock showing trilobites from Humber Gorge, Newfoundland. The other is for a part/counterpart of Sphaeragnostus boya from Cormorant Head, Newfoundland. Both forms are in this archive. The two specimens are likely still with the Princeton material; they cannot be located at the Peabody., 1935-1936; 002693
    - Old loan form for fusulinid specimens loaned from the University of Kansas Geological Museum., 1938; 002697
    - List of returned specimens with no records in the file. Two lots. The first was 9 specimens of Lissatrypa atheroides from Anticosti. The second was assorted specimens from Coahuila, Mexico., Mar 1962; 002699
  - Manuscript Material., 001266
    - Divisional notes. Abstracts and Excursion Guide: 15th Field Conference of the Cambrian Stage Subdivision Working Group International Subcommision on Cambrian Startigraphy, 000949
    - Manuscript material. Manuscript on stratigraphy: Canada., 1939; 000220
    - Manuscript material. Plates, photos, maps, correspondence, loans, and negatives from Yang's incomplete PhD dissertation on Mollusca of Traverse Grp, Michigan., 1939; 000641
    - Manuscript material. manuscript and other loc. info.: South Dakota, Nebraska, Kansas, Colorado., 1944; 000400
    - Manuscript material. Yale A.B. thesis ms. with locality info.: South Dakota., 1959; 000440
    - Manuscript material. Plate explanations for Bretsky (1970) including brachipopods, bivalves and gastropods; dissertation., 000628
    - Manuscript material. Ph.D. dissertation, photocopied portions: The Natural Growth Records of Reef Building Corals and other related locality data: Bermuda, Barbados., 1978; 000269
    - Manuscript material. Copies of papers and abstracts that Huber used in doing his 2003 paper with McDonald and Olsen on Jurassic insects Newark supergroup (reprint # 5380); Mormolucoides, 000780
    - Manuscript material. Copy of April, 1990 report, "Shore Protection and Erosion Control Project, Detailed Project Report and Environmental Assessment, Prospect Beach, West Haven, Connecticut"; Holocene, Post-glacial concretions., 2003; 000783
    - Manuscript material. Poster and manuscript: Observations on Onychaster (Ophiuroidea: Onychasteridae) (Famennian - Visean age)" 7th European Conference on Echinoderms, Gottingen, 2010, 000966
    - Manuscript material. New eurypterids from the Upper Silurian Bertie Group of New York State: Rhinocarcinosoma eatoni n. sp. and Paracarcinosoma vaningenie (Clark and Ruedemann); unpublished manuscript, 000827
    - Manuscript material. Unpublished manuscripts and papers of S.J. Ciurca. Also, abstracts from poster sessions., 000842
    - Manuscript material. unpublished Postilla MS on Triassic crayfish, North Carolina, 000875
    - Manuscript material. Bambach Thesis Types - Master List (in progress), 000897
    - Manuscript material. Photographs, slides, and negatives used in "A pictorial guide to fossils" by Gerard R. Case (ISBN 0442226519)., 003186
    - Miscellaneous. Copy of "Reconnaissance from Carroll to the Yellowstone..." 1875; with sections by E.S. Dana and G.B. Grinnell, and R.P. Whitfield: Ludlow Expedition Montana., 1876; 000333
    - Miscellaneous. Gastropod predation in the type Fox Hills Formation. unpublished notes., 1978; 000532
    - Miscellaneous. G. Arthur Cooper Papers, 1904-1987, 1993, with related material from 1865-1892. Smithsonian Archives. [Volume=Record Unit 7318], 000424
    - Miscellaneous. St. Jean Annotated Stromatoporoid Bibliography, 000896
    - Papers, notes, correspondence. Papers and notes relevant to J. Brookes Knight's dissertation collection (photocopy of partial dissertation): Missouri. 1927, 1928, 1929, 1930, 1931, 000350
    - Publication Materials. Willis W. Tyrrell - Figures, tables, plates and specimen photography from Ross and Tyrrell (1965); handwritten and xeroxed copies of Dry Canyon section (Whetstone Mts) from W.W. Tyrrell; xeroxed copies of H.R. Wanless' Dry Canyon section and field notes., 002766
    - Photomicrographs and Eastman glass plates of Laqueus californicus (IPS.003606.A-F), some used in Cloud's 1942 paper (IPR.00209)., 02 Dec 1939; 002686
    - Petrified Wood: The journal of the Petrified Wood Society. Vol. 1, no. 1 and vol. 2, no. 3., 1963-1964; 003145
    - [Untitled], 000980
    - Manuscript material including an early draft, stratigraphic sections, and correspondence for IPR.15155 "New Silurian cooksonias from dolostones of north-eastern North America", 003187
    - Unpublished manuscript regarding a new eurypterid horizon in the Moran Corner Waterlime (Silurian, New York), 003218
    - unpublished manuscript. Beecher's Trilobite Bed: The History of the Quarries, unpublished manuscript documenting the history of Beecher's Trilobite Bed, Rome, New York by property owner (early 2000s) John S. Koziarz, 2013; 002429
  - Miscellaneous. Miscellaneous Archives from the division of Invertebrate Paleontology., 001305
    - Locality information. Mississippian Renault Limestone, Waterloo, IL, 2009; 000914
    - Miscellaneous. Notices in American Journal of Science: Syria; Lebanon; Egypt; Palestine; & other info. 1821-1865, 000289
    - Miscellaneous. Expense Report: Virginia., 1911; 000257
    - Miscellaneous. Memorandum, "Long Point and Clam Bank formations, western Newfoundland"; plus map. 1963 - 1965, 000458
    - Miscellaneous. Field trip and seminar on the Fort Payne Formation. Pages; 35, 2004; 000804
    - Miscellaneous. Posters from "Frontiers in Paleontology and Geomicrobiology" - a two day seminar at Yale University (May 14-15, 2010). Pages; 5., 000937
    - Miscellaneous. Assorted photographs and copies of sketches of eurypterid and scorpionid material with notes, most likely sent to Ciurca by Kjellesvig-Waering., 003142
    - Papers, notes, correspondence. List of books used by Stoyanov, while he was at Yale, in making his report to Sinclair Oil Co.: Timor., 1922; 000363
    - A series of protocols and correspondence discussing museum and division policies regarding loans, and storage of specimens and archives., 1974-2015; 002720
    - A series of correspondence discussing the ownership of certain paintings housed in the invertebrate paleontology collections., 1993-2005; 002691
    - Lists of users of various IPV prefix ranges. This includes both student workers and volunteers, as well as the starting number for each number range as of January 2018., 2005-present; 003216
    - Prints made from wood blocks found in the collections. The prints were made by Gwen Antell on the Pierson College letter press. Prints include stratigraphic figures, paleogeographic maps, Brachiopongiid images, paleobotany images, etc., 2015-2016; 002717
    - Pencil sketch (bryozoan?) found with J.W. Stovall Collection bryozoan photographs dated 1927 and withB.Nekhoroshev typed paper on bryozoan:Semicoscinium dated1928 and with miscellaneous bryozoan labels. Found in Invertebrate Paleontology Collection drawer at end of systematic Bryozoa collection., 002485
    - J.W. Stovall Collection bryozoan photographs dated 1927 found with B.Nekhoroshev 1928 typed paper on bryozoan:Semicoscinium, and with Pencil sketch (bryozoan?) and with miscellaneous bryozoan labels. Found in Invertebrate Paleontology Collection drawer at end of systematic Bryozoa collection., 002486
    - B.Nekhoroshev 1928 typed paper on bryozoan:Semicoscinium, found with J.W. Stovall Collection bryozoan photographs dated 1927, and with Pencil sketch (bryozoan?), and with miscellaneous bryozoan labels. Found in Invertebrate Paleontology Collection drawer at end of systematic Bryozoa collection., 002487
  - Phylogeny of Curators., 001304
    - Miscellaneous. History of Peabody Museum; phylogeny of curators; Invertebrate Paleontology; including mostly reprints., 2003; 000777
  - Well Core Information., 001303
    - Divisional notes. Bryozoa samples in well cores of Carter Oil Co. Coll. should be discarded unless shown otherwise., 000880
    - Miscellaneous. well logs of Derby Oil Co.; Kansas. 1925-1927, 000395
    - Miscellaneous. list of core depths: Texas., 1944; 000401
  - locality card catalog. Invertebrate Paleontology Division card catalog of localities (old)., 002705
- Collection Information, Series VII
  - Collection Cards & Labels. Various collection cards and labels associated with the Division of Invertebrate Paleontology., 001299
    - Card file. copies of Princeton catalog cards, 1905; 000505
    - Card file. cc of Princeton catalog cards; Wyoming., 1930; 000506
    - Card file. cc of Princeton catalog cards; Wyoming., 1930; 000507
    - Miscellaneous. Old exhibit labels & original specimen labels (see also doc. 328) for specimens that were removed from exhibit (Invertebrate Hall) in late 1940 or those that are still on exhibit (1992)., 000362
    - Miscellaneous. Extra labels from Dartmouth College (no corresponding specimens), 000860
    - Papers, notes, correspondence. Information card for coll. of Traverse Grp fossils: Michigan., 1949; 000293
    - Thirteen envelopes containing the old drawer labels from Peabody Room 5. As drawers were brought up from the Paleozoic Stratigraphic Collection and incorporated into the Systematic Collection, the drawer labels were removed and archived. Each folder contains a spreadsheet listing which drawer labels are in the envelope., 002706
    - Assorted disassociated labels that arrived in the IP division with amber material from Entomology. Attempts were made to reunite labels with specimens, but the labels in this archive could not be reunited., 002773
  - Collection Notes., 001301
    - Locality information. Exhibit label: 'Crinoids and other marine animals from the bottom of the Lower Devonic sea'. Slab of Lower Devonian Coeymans crinoids. Second floor of Peabody at the east entrance to the Sachem wing. ca 1905, 000533
    - Miscellaneous. History of brachiospongid fossils of Kentucky: Kentucky., 1867; 000240
    - Miscellaneous. Notes on Chester Reeds accessions: Oklahoma., 1923; 000234
    - Miscellaneous. Update of taxonomy of Triassic Ammonoidea in systematic collection (including corrections of existing spelling errors)., 2000; 000737
    - Miscellaneous. Scientific and acquistion notes, X-rays, on Bdellacoma specimens from Hotchkiss and Glass, 2007(?) - IPR.5778, 000859
    - Papers, notes, correspondence. Notes on 'Paleontology of Kentucky': Kentucky., 1919; 000171
    - Papers, notes, correspondence. Elmo, Kansas, Permian; Insect classification used by Bethoux in cataloging coll., 2005; 000877
    - Papers, notes, correspondence. Report on the research potential of the Joseph St. Jean, Jr. stromatoporoid collection donated to the Yale Peabody Museum, 2012; 000982
    - Papers, notes, correspondence. Notes on the Ciurca Collection, 000917
    - Images and notes related to adding specimens (vials, sediment, slides) from the Hull Lab to the IP collection., 15 May 2018; 003215
    - Photographs of the collection space in room 218, Kline Geology Laboratory (KGL) from the May Dasch era., 1965-1966; 002719
    - Notes with locality information and foram identification for well slides., 2017; 003217
    - Notes regarding the fossil insect collection (types catalogued and present). Also includes material that came with the amber collection., 002696
  - Loan & Sale Forms. Loan and sale information associated with the collection of Invertebrate Paleontology., 001300
    - Miscellaneous. Notice of Fossil Collections For Sale: Europe., 000202
    - Miscellaneous. Notes on disposition of YPM loan of Ordovician nautiloids: Newfoundland., 000330
    - Miscellaneous. Survey of the Princeton University Invertebrate Paleontology collections as part of bid to get them; including Eurypterus latus; Gerta Keller, 000820
    - Miscellaneous. Specimens requested for use in new Stromatoporoidea Treatise, 000905
    - Miscellaneous. Old completed loan forms, 000940
    - Annotated loan form for two specimens of Nereidavus varians loaned to C. Croneis in 1933., 1933-1967; 002690
    - Loan forms and correspondence related to IP.017110 - a series of specimens of Iocrinus subcrassus loaned to R. C. Moore for study. 4 specimens from the original lot of 7 are still missing, including the calyx published in Moore, 1962 (pl.2, f.1)., 1942-1980; 002689
- Electronic Archives, Series VIII
  Scope and Contents
  Former IPE Series.
  - Electronic Archives., 002431